<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno Regni Caroli II. Regis Scotiæ Angliæ Franciæ &amp; Hiberniæ duodecimo at the Parliament begun at Westminster, the five and twentieth day of April, Anno Dom. 1660, in the twelfth year of the reign of our most Gracious Soveraign Lord Charles, by the grace of God, of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, King, defender of the faith, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Laws, statutes, etc.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1144B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175044</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61296992</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61296992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180550</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180550)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2833:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno Regni Caroli II. Regis Scotiæ Angliæ Franciæ &amp; Hiberniæ duodecimo at the Parliament begun at Westminster, the five and twentieth day of April, Anno Dom. 1660, in the twelfth year of the reign of our most Gracious Soveraign Lord Charles, by the grace of God, of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, King, defender of the faith, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Laws, statutes, etc.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bill and Christopher Barker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title vignette: royal arms.</note>
                  <note>At bottom of t.p. : "And reprinted at Dublin by William Bladen, Anno Dom. 1660."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and tightly bound with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pardon --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Indemnity --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1660 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180550:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180550:1"/>
            <p>Anno Regni CAROLI II. <hi>REGIS</hi> Angliae, Scotiae, Franciae, <hi>&amp;</hi> Hiberniae, DVODECIMO.</p>
            <p>At the Parliament begun at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the Five and twentieth day of <hi>April, Anno Domini</hi> 1660.</p>
            <p>In the Twelfth year of the Reign of Our moſt Gracious Soveraign Lord CHARLES, by the Grace of God, of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> King, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Bill</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Barker,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie, 1660, <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M PRIVILEGIO.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Reprinted at <hi>Dublin</hi> by <hi>William Bladen Anno Dom.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:180550:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180550:2"/>
            <head>Anno Regni CAROLI II.</head>
            <head type="sub">AN OF ACT Free and General Pardon, INDEMPNITY AND OBLIVION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty taking into his Gracious and Serious conſideration the long and great Troubles Diſcords, and Wars, that have for many years paſt been in this Kingdom, And that divers of his Subjects are by occaſion thereof, and otherwiſe, faln into and be obnoxious to great pains and penalties: Out of a hearty and pious Deſire to put an end to all Suits and Controverſies, that by occaſion of the late Diſtractions have ariſen or may ariſe between all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, And to the intent that no Crime whatſoever committed againſt his Majeſty or his Royal Father, ſhall hereafter riſe in Judgment, or be brought in Queſtion againſt any of them to the leaſt endamagement of them, either in their Lives, Liberties, Eſtates, or to the prejudice of their Reputations, by any Reproach or Term of Diſtinction; And to bury all Seeds of future Diſcords and remembrance of the former, aſwell in his own breaſt as in the breaſts of his Subjects one towards another: And in performance of his Royal and Gracious Word, ſignified by his Letters to the ſeveral Houſes of Parliament now Aſſembled, and his Declarations in that behalf publiſhed, Is pleaſed that it may be Enacted, And be it Enacted by the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, with the Advice and Conſent of the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, Firſt, That all and all manner of Treaſons. Miſpriſions of Treaſon, Murthers, Felonies, Offences, Crimes, Contempts and Miſdemeanors, Counſelled, Commanded, Acted or Done ſince the firſt day of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> in the year of our Lord, 1637. by any perſon or perſons before the 24. day of <hi>June,</hi> in the year of our Lord, 1660 other then the perſons hereafter by name Excepted, in ſuch manner as they are hereafter Excepted, by virtue or colour of any Command, Power, Authority, Commiſſion, Warrant or Inſtructions from his late Majeſty King CHARLES, or his Majeſty that now is, or from any other perſon or perſons, deriving or pretending to derive Authority, mediately or immediately from both or either of their Majeſties, or by virtue or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of any Authority derived mediately or immediately of or from both Houſes, or either Houſe of Parliament, or of, or from any Convention or Aſſembly, called or reputed, or taking on them the Name of a Parliament, Or by, from, or under any Authority ſtiled or known by the Name of the Keepers of the Libertie of <hi>England,</hi> by Authority of Parliament, Or by virtue or colour of any Writ, Commiſſion, Letters Patents, Inſtruction or Inſtructions of or from any perſon or perſons, Tituled, reputed, or taken to be Lord Protector of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereunto belonging, or Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions and Territories thereto belonging, or aſſuming the Authority or reputed to be chief Magiſtrate of the Commonwealth, or Commander in chief of the Forces or Armies of this Nation by Sea or Land, or by any Pretence, Warrant, or Command whatſoever, from them or any of them, or their or either of their reſpective Councils, or Council, or any Member of ſuch Council or Councils, or from any perſon or perſons whatſoever, deriving or pretending to derive Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from them, or any of them, be Pardoned, Releaſed, Indempnified, Diſcharged, and put in utter Oblivion.</p>
            <p>And that all and every the perſon and perſons, Acting, Adviſing, Aſſiſting, Abetting, and Counſelling the ſame, they, their Heirs, Executors, and Adminiſtrators, (Except as before is excepted) be and are hereby Pardoned, Releaſed, Acquitted, Indempnified, and
<pb facs="tcp:180550:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſcharged from the ſame: And of and from all pains of death, and other pains, Judgments, Indictments, Convictions, Attainders, Outlawries, Penalties, Eſcheats and Forfeitures therefore had or given, or that might accrew for the ſame; And that all ſuch Judgments, Indictments, Convictions, Attainders, Outlawries, Penalties, Eſcheats and Forfeitures, and every of them, and all Grants thereupon made, and all Eſtates derived under the ſame, be and are hereby Declared and Enacted to be from henceforth Null and void. And that all mean profits not yet received by ſuch Grantees ſhall be, and are hereby diſcharged: And that all and every perſon and perſons, bodies Politick and Corporate, their and every of their Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators and Succeſſors, ſhall be and are hereby reſtored to all and every their Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, Goods, Chattels and other things Forfeited, which to his Majeſty do or ſhall appertain by reaſon of any offence herein before mentioned, and not hereafter in this preſent Act excepted and forepriſed.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted, That all Appeals, and all perſonal Actions, Suits, Moleſtations and Proſecutions whatſoever, for or by reaſon of any act of Hoſtility, Treſpaſs, Aſſault, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment or breach of the Peace, Adviſed, Counſelled, Commanded, appointed, Happened, Acted or done by reaſon of the late Troubles, or the late Wars in his Majeſties Dominions, or relating thereunto, and all Judgments and Executions thereupon had before the Firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> in the year of our Lord, 1658. ſtand and be from henceforth diſcharged; But not to reſtore to any perſon or perſons any ſums of money, mean Profits or Goods already received or taken upon ſuch Execution, or to give any account for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And be it likewiſe Enacted, That all Appeals and all perſonal Actions and Cauſes of ſuch Actions, Suites, Moleſtations and Proſecutions whatſoever, for or by reaſon of any Act or thing Adviſed, Counſelled, Commanded, Acted or done by virtue or colour of any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or Commiſſion granted by his late Majeſty, or his Majeſty that now is, or by virtue or colour of any Order or Ordinance of one or both Houſes of Parliament ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> Or by any Act or Order made by any perſons aſſuming the Name of a Parliament, and ſitting as a Parliament at <hi>Westminſter</hi> after the death of the late King CHARLES the Firſt; Or by the Authority of the ſaid Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England;</hi> Or by any Ordinance by either of the late Protectors and Council; Or by or upon any Commiſſion, Writ, Procels, or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant by them or any of them, or by Authority derived from them or any of them: And all demands of Arrearages of Rents and mean Profits of Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments heretofore incurred or grown due, which have beed paid, received or diſpoſed by virtue or colour of any the Authorities or pretended Authorities aforeſaid; other then ſuch Arrearages or mean Profits as are or ſhall be otherwiſe diſpoſed by any Act, or Acts of this preſent Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Parliament, be from henceforth diſcharged.</p>
            <p>And it is further by the Authority aforeſaid Enacted in the ſecond place, That all and every the Subjects of theſe his Majeſties Realms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> the Iſles of <hi>Ierſey</hi> and <hi>Garnſey,</hi> and the Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> and other his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions, the Heirs, Executors, and Adminiſtrators of them, and every of them, and all and ſingular Bodies in any manner of wiſe Corporated, Cities, Burroughs. Shires, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings Hundreds, Lathes, Rapes, Wappentakes, Towns, Villages, Hamlets and Tythings, and every of them, and the Succeſſor and Succeſſors of every of them, ſhall be, and are by the Authority of this preſent Parliament Acquitted, Pardoned, Releaſed, Indempnified and Diſcharged againſt the Kings Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, and every of them, of and from all manner of Treaſons, Miſpriſions of Treaſon, Felonies, Offences, Contempts, Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, Entries, Wrongs, Deceits, Miſdemeanors, Forfeitures, Penalties, and ſums of Money, Intruſions, Mean Profits, Wardſhips, Marriages, Reliefs, Liveries, Ouſter le mains, Mean Rates, Reſpits of Homage, Fines and Seiſures for Alienation without Licence, Arrearages of Rents, (other then the Arrearages of Rents due from the late Farmers, or pretended Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the Excize or Cuſtoms reſpectively, and other then ſuch Arrearages of Rents, or Mean Profits, as are or ſhall be otherwiſe diſpoſed by any Act or Acts of this preſent Parliament) and of and from all Arrearages of Tenths and Firſt Fruits, Fines, Poſt-Fines, Iſſues and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciaments, and all Recognizances, Bonds, or other Securities given for Payment of them, or any of them, Concealments of Cuſtomes and Excize, Arrearages of Purveyance, and of Compoſitions for the ſame, and of and from all Pains of Death, Pains Corporal and Pecuniary, and generally of and from all other Things, Cauſes, Quarrels, Suits, Judgments and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in this preſent Act hereafter not Excepted nor Foreprized, which may be or can be by his Majeſty in any wiſe, or by any means Pardoned, before and unto the 24. day of <hi>Iune,</hi> in the year of our Lord, 1660. to every or any of his ſaid Subjects, Bodies Corporate, Cities, Burroughs, Shires, Ridings, Hundreds, Lathes, Rapes, Wappentakes, Towns, Villages and Tithings, or any of them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:180550:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all Grants and Patents ſince the 25. of <hi>March,</hi> 1641. touching the Wardſhip and Cuſtody of the Body and Lands, or touching the Marriage of any Heir within Age, and all Mean Profits yet unreceived, and demandable by reaſon thereof, ſhall be, and are hereby from henceforth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged.</p>
            <p>And alſo the Kings Majeſty is contented, That it be further Enacted by Authority of this preſent Parliament, and be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That this his ſaid Free Pardon, Indemnity and Oblivion ſhall be as good and effectual in the Law to every of his ſaid Subjects, Bodies Corporate, and others before rehearſed, in, for, and againſt all things which be not hereafter in this preſent Act excepted and foreprized, as the ſame Pardon, Indemnity and Oblivion ſhould have been, if all Offenſes, Contempts, Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Cauſes, Matters, Suits, Quarrels, Judgments, Executions, Penalties, and all other things, not hereafter in this preſent Act Excepted and Foreprized, had been particularly, ſingularly, eſpecially, and plainly named, rehearſed and ſpecified, and alſo pardoned by proper and expreſs words and names, in their kinds, natures and qualities, by words and terms thereunto requiſite to have been put in, and expreſſed in this preſent Act of Free Pardon, Indemnity and Oblivion: And that his ſaid Subjects nor any of them, nor the Heirs, Executors, or Adminiſtrators of any of them, nor the ſaid Bodies corporate, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before-named and rehearſed, nor any of them, be, nor ſhall be ſued, vexed, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted, by, or on the behalf of the Kings Majeſty, his Heirs or Succeſſors, in their bodies, Goods, Chattels, Lands or Tenements, for any manner of Matter, Cauſe, Contempt, Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanor, Forfeiture, Treſpaſs, Offenſe, or any other thing ſuffered, done, or committed before the ſaid 24. day of <hi>June</hi> 1660. againſt His late Majeſtie King <hi>Charls,</hi> or his Majeſty that now is, His Crown, Dignity, Prerogative, Laws or Statutes, but onely for ſuch Matters, Cauſes and Offenſes as be excepted and fore-prized by this preſent Act out of the ſame, any Statute or Statutes, Laws, Cuſtoms, or Uſages heretofore had, made or uſed to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding: And that all and every the Kings ſaid Subjects, and all and ſingular the Bodies Corporate, and others before rehearſed, may by him or themſelves, or by his or their Deputie or Deputies, or by his or their Attorney or Attorneys, according to the Laws of this Realm, plead and miniſter this preſent Act of Free Pardon, for his or their Diſcharge, of or for any thing that is by virtue of this preſent Act, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, diſcharged, given or granted, without any Fee or other thing, paying to any perſon or perſons for writing or entry of the Judgments or other Cauſe concerning ſuch Plea, Writing, or Entry, but onely ſixteen pence to be paid to the Officer or Clerk that ſhall enter ſuch Plea, Matter, or Judgment, for the parties Diſcharge in that behalf, any Law, Statute, Uſage or Cuſtom to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And furthermore the Kings Majeſty is contented and pleaſed, That it be Enacted, and be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That this his ſaid Free Pardon, Indempnity and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion, by the general Words, Clauſes and Sentences before rehearſed, ſhall be reputed deemed, adjudged, expounded, allowed, and taken in all manner of Courts of His Highneſs and elſwhere moſt beneficial and available to all and ſingular the ſaid Subjects, Bodies Corporate, and others before rehearſed, and to every of them in all things, not in this preſent Act excepted or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, without any ambiguity, queſtion, or other delay whatſoever it ſhall be, to be made, pleaded, objected or alleadged by the King our Soveraign Lord, His Heirs or Succeſſors, or by his or their General Attorney or Atorneys, or by any perſon or perſons for his Highneſs, or any of his Heirs or Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>And furthermore be it Enacted by the King our Soveraign Lord, and by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any Officer or Clerk of any of his Highneſs Courts, commonly called the Chancery, Kings-Bench, and Common-Pleas, or of his Exchequer, or any other Officer or Clerk of any other of his Highneſs Courts within this Realm, at any time after the paſſing of this preſent Act, make out, or write out any manner of Writs, Proceſs, Summons, or other Precepts, whereby any of the ſaid Subjects, or any of the ſaid Bodies corporated; or others before rehearſed, or any of them ſhall be in any wiſe Arreſted, Attached, Diſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Summoned, or otherwiſe Vexed, Inquieted, or grieved in his or their Bodies, Lands, Tenements, Goods, or Chattels, or in any of them, for, or becauſe of any manner of thing pardoned or diſcharged by virtue of this Act of Free Pardon; or if any Sheriff or Eſcheator, or any of their Deputy or Deputies, or any Bayliff or other Officer what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, by colour of his or their Office, or otherwiſe, after the paſſing of this preſent Act, do levy, receive, take, or withhold of or from any Perſon or Perſons, any thing pardoned or diſcharged by this Act; That then every ſuch Perſon ſo offending and thereof lawfully
<pb facs="tcp:180550:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180550:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180550:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>convicted or condemned by any ſufficient teſtimony, witneſs, or proof, ſhall yield and pay for recompence thereof to the party ſo grieved or offended thereby, his or their treble damages, beſides all coſts of the Suit, and ſhall alſo forfeit and loſe to the Kings Majeſty for every ſuch deſault Ten pounds: And nevertheleſs all and ſingular ſuch Writts, Proceſs and Precepts ſo to be made for, or upon any manner of thing pardoned or diſcharged by this preſent Act of Free Pardon, Indempnity and Oblivion, ſhall be utterly void and of none effect.</p>
            <p>Except and always foreprized out of this Free and general Pardon, all Murders done or committed by any Perſon or Perſons other than ſuch which are Pardoned and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged in the firſt Clauſe of Pardon above mentioned: And alſo excepted and always foreprized out of this General and Free Pardon all and every offences of Piracie and Robbery done upon the Seas, not done in relation to the Differences and Wars aforeſaid, and every procuring or abetting of any ſuch Offenders, and the comforting and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of them, or any of them, or any Goods taken by way of ſuch Piracy or Robbery upon the Seas as aforeſaid: And alſo excepted the deteſtable and abominable Vice of Buggery committed with Mankinde or Beaſt: And alſo excepted all Rapes and carnal Raviſhments of Women: And alſo excepted all Raviſhments, and wilfull taking away, or manying of any Maid, Widow, or Damſel againſt her will, or without the aſſent or agreement of her Parents, or of ſuch as then had her in Cuſtody; and alſo all Offenſes of aiding, comforting, procuring, or abetting of any ſuch Raviſhment, wilfull taking or Marrying, had, committed or done: And alſo excepted all offences made Felony by a certain Act made and ordained, Entituled, <hi>An Act to reſtrain all Perſons from Marriage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till their former Wives and former Huſhands be dead:</hi> And alſo excepted all offences of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, Conjurations, Witchcrafts, Sorceries, Inchantments, and Charms; and all offences of procuring abetting, or comforting of the ſame: and all perſons now attainted or convicted of any the ſaid excepted Offences: And alſo excepted all and ſingular the Accompts of all and every perſon and perſons appointed by any of the Authorities, or pretended Authorities aforeſaid, to be Treaſurer, Receiver, Farmer or Collector, (other than the Sub-Collectors of the ſeveral Pariſhes, Towns and Hamlets reſpectively, for, and concerning their Receipts before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. day of <hi>June</hi> in the year of our Lord 1659) who have received or collected any Subſidie, Cuſtome, Subſidie of Tonnage and Poundage, Prize-goods, Aſſeſsment, Sequeſtration, New Impoſt or Exciſe, or of any the Rents and Revenues of any Lands or Hereditaments, of or belonging unto the late King, Queen, or Prince, or King that now is, or belonging to the late Arch-Biſhopricks, Biſhopricks, Deans, or Deans and Chapters, Canons, Prebends, and other Officers belonging to any Cathedral or Collegiate Church, or Popiſh Recuſants convict, or of Perſons Sequeſtered for their Recuſancie, or other ſequeſtred Eſtates Received or Collected by, or paid unto them ſince the 30. of <hi>January</hi> in the year of our Lord 1642; and of all Moneys and other Duties grown due or contracted upon the Sale or Diſpoſition of them, or any of them.</p>
            <p>Provided, That the Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators or Tertenants of the Lands of any Accomptant within this Exception now deceaſed, ſhall not be charged with, nor liable unto any Accompt for the matters in this Exception mentioned: Except for ſuch Sum or Sums of Money as remain due upon any of their Accompts already ſtated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and are not yet payd in, and that no Accomptant as aboveſaid, now living, ſhall be liable to make accompt of any Sum or Sums of Money, payd or disburſed, or otherwiſe allowed, or diſcharged, by virtue or colour of any Order or Ordinances of both or either Houſe or Houſes of Parliament, or any Convention or Aſſembly called, or Reputed, or taking on them the name of a Parliament, or of <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Protector, or of <hi>Richard</hi> his Son, while he continued, or was ſtiled, or obeyed as Protector, or by any Perſons acting as a Committee appointed by the ſaid two Houſes, or either of them, or by any ſuch Convention, or Aſſembly, or any Order or Direction of ſuch Committee or Committees, or any Perſon or Perſons acting as a Publick Council, though having no legal Authority ſo to do, or by their, or any their Order or Orders, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>It being further Declared and Enacted, and is Enacted by the Authoritie aforeſaid. That no perſon or perſons ſhall be charged for any Moneys by him received for the Fees, Salaries, and Wages then allowed, or for Moneys by him disburſed upon any publick uſe, or pretence, though the Direction, or Authority whereby the ſame Money was Iſſued, was not, or be not Legal and Warrantable in Law.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:180550:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And be it further Provided, That no Military, or Commiſſioned Officer of the Armies, or Navies, or Souldier, or Mariner, who before the 25. of <hi>March,</hi> 1659. hath received any Moneys for his own Pay, or the Pay of other Souldiers, or for any other Contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies of the Souldiers, or Guarriſons under his Command, or by way of reward, ſhall be called to accompt therefore.</p>
            <p>And that no perſon whatſoever ſhall be called to accompt for any the matters in this Exception mentioned, after the 24. of <hi>June.</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord God, 1662. now next enſuing; And that in caſe any perſon who ſtands accomptable for any moneys received ſince the firſt of <hi>January,</hi> 1642, and before the 30. of <hi>January</hi> 1648, have been robb'd, or plundered by Souldiers, or others, of the monies in their hands, or of any Notes, or Books of receipt, touching their payments or diſcharge, Then the oath or oaths of ſuch party or parties of the ſame reſpectively, ſhall be a good diſcharge for ſo much of their accompt. And that the Oath of every Accomptant in or between the years, 1642, and 1648. of what they have paid to any publick uſe, by, or accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to any publick or pretended Order or Authority whatſoever, ſhall be a good diſcharge, as to ſo much of the accompt of ſuch perſon or perſons. And except all Firſt fruits and tenths in the hands of any Receiver not having disburſed, as in the laſt Exception is expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Provided, That all and every Judgment of Diſcharge, or <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> had, or given at any time upon any accompt in the Publique Exchequer, ſince the year 1648, be allowed, and ſhall not be avoided; except all accompts of the Revenues of Churches and Vicaridges in <hi>Wales,</hi> and the County of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and all Judgments of diſcharge, or <hi>quietus</hi> thereupon obtained, and alſo Excepted out of this Pardon all offences of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, Perjuries and the Subornation of Perjury, or Witneſſes and Offences of Forging or Counterfeiting any Deeds, Debentures, Bills of Publick Faith, Eſcripts, Wills, or other Writings whatſoever, or of any Examinations or Teſtimonies of any Witneſs or Witneſſes, tending to bring any perſon or perſons in danger of his Life, Liberty, or Eſtate, and the giving the ſame in evidence, and the compelling or procuring of any ſuch counterfeiting or forging to be had or made.</p>
            <p>And who excepted all Offences in detaining, imbeſling, or purloining any the Goods, Money, Chattels or Jewels of the late King, Queen, or Prince, or any of the children of the late King and Queen, other then Shipping, Stores, and Ammunitions of War, and other then ſuch Goods and Chattels as have been ſold or diſpoſed of to any of the Servants or Creditors of his late Majeſty, in, or toward ſatisfaction of their Debts or Wages.</p>
            <p>And alſo Excepted out of this Pardon, all Iſſues, Fines, and Amercements, Rents, and other Publick Duties being Leavyed, Received or collected by any Sheriff, under-Sheriff, Bayliff, Miniſter, or other Officer, to, or for the uſe of the late King, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or the ſaid Keepers of the Liberty of <hi>England,</hi> or any other perſon ſtiling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Protector or for his Majeſty that now is, and not accompted for, and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p>And alſo Excepted out of this Pardon, all and every offence and offences committed or done by any Jeſuite, Seminary, or <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt whatſoever, contrary to the Tenor or Effect of the Statute made in the 27, year of the Reign of the late Queen <hi>Eliſabeth,</hi> Entituled, <hi>An Act againſt Jeſuites, Seminaries, Prieſts, and other diſobedient Perſons,</hi> or of any part thereof, and all Out-lawries, Proceedings, Judgments, and Executions for the ſame offences, or any of them.</p>
            <p>Provided always, and be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that it ſhall and may be lawful, to, and for all and every Clerk, and other Officer of the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to award and make Writs of <hi>Capias <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tlagatum,</hi> at the ſuit of the Party Plaintiff, againſt ſuch Perſons Out-layed, as be pardoned by this Act, to the intent to compell the Defendant, or Defendants to make anſwer, to the Plaintiff or Plaintiffs, at whoſe Suit, he or they were Out lawed. And that every perſon ſo Out lawed ſhall ſue a Writ of <hi>Scire Facias,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Party or Parties, at whoſe Suit he or they were ſo Out-lawed, before this Pardon in that behalf ſhall be allowed him or them ſo Out-lawed.</p>
            <p>Provided, and be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid; That this Act of General Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, ſhall not in any wiſe extend to Pardon any Out-lawries upon any Writ of <hi>Capias ad Satisfaciendum,</hi> until ſuch time as the Party ſo Out-lawed ſhall ſatisfy, or otherwiſe agree with the Party at whoſe Suit the ſame Perſon was ſo Out-lawed or Condemned.</p>
            <p>And alſo excepted out of this Pardon all Informations and other Proceedings Depending,
<pb facs="tcp:180550:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Concerning any Common High-ways or Bridges, and all Iſſues, returned upon any Proceſs, concerning the ſame, ſince the 30 day of <hi>January,</hi> 1648; Except alſo all Recognizances, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations and other Securities given, or Entred into, ſince the 25. of <hi>March,</hi> 1640, by any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, Reeve, Bailiff, Collector, or other Accountant in the Court of the Publick Exchequer, and their Sureties and their Accounts Reſpectively.</p>
            <p>Provided always, and be it Enacted; That this Act or any thing therein Contained, ſhall not extend, or be Conſtrued to Pardon, or Diſcharge any Recognizance, Obligation or Bond which is not yet forfeited.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid; That all Acts of Hoſtilitie and Injuries, whether between the late King, and the Lords and Commons then in Parliament aſſembled; or between any of the People of this Nation, which did ariſe upon any Action, Attempt, Aſſiſtance, Council, or Advice, having Relation unto, or falling out by reaſon of the late Troubles, or in the late Warrs, or Publick Differences between the late King and Parliament, or between his now Majeſty, or any of his Subjects, and which are not in this Act excepted; that the ſame and whatſoever hath enſued thereupon, whether trenching upon the Laws and Liberties of this Nation, or upon the Honour of his Majeſty, or upon the Honour of Authority of the Parliament, or to the prejudice of any Particular or Private Perſon, ſhall in no time, from and after the 24. of <hi>June,</hi> in the year of our Lord 1660. be called in queſtion, whatſoever be the quality of the Perſon, or of whatſoever Kind or Degree, Civil or Criminal, the Injury is ſuppoſed to be; And that no mention be made thereof in time to come in judgment or judicial proceedings.</p>
            <p>And to the intent and purpoſe that all names and terms of diſtinction may be likewiſe put into utter Oblivion, Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid; That if any Perſon or Perſons, within the ſpace of three years next enſuing, ſhall preſume maliciouſly to call or alledge of, or object againſt any other Perſon or Perſons, any Name or Names or other words of Reproach, any way tending to revive the Memory of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te Differences or the Occaſions thereof; That then every ſuch perſon, ſo as aforeſaid Offending ſhall Forfeit and Pay, unto the Party Grieved, in Caſe ſuch Party offending ſhall be of the Degree of a Gentleman or above, ten Pounds; and if under that Degree the Sum of forty Shillings, to be recovered by the Partie grieved, by Action of Debt to be therefore brought in any of his Majeſties Courts of Record, wherein no E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oign, Protection, or Wager of Law ſhall be allowed, or any more than one Imparlance, ſo as the ſame Action be commenced or proſecuted within ſix Months next after the Offence Committed: And if the Jury ſworn to try any Iſſue or Iſſues that ſhall be joyned in ſuch Action ſhall find for the Plaintiff, they ſhall likewiſe give to every ſuch Plaintiff forty ſhllings Damages, over and above the Penalty aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Provided, always that this Act, or any thing therein contained ſhall not extend, or give any Benefit to any Perſon or Perſons, who have had any hand in the Plotting, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving, or deſigning the Great and Heinous Rebellion of <hi>IRELAND</hi> mentioned in one Act paſſed in the Parliament, begun at <hi>WESTMINSTER</hi> the 3. day of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> In the ſixteenth year of King CHARLES Entituled, <hi>An Act for the speedy and effectual Reducing of the Rebels in his Majeſties Kingdom of IRELAND to their due obedience, to his Majesty and Crown of ENGLAND,</hi> Or in Aiding, Aſſiſting, or Abetting the ſame: (other then ſuch as by another Act intended hereafter to be paſſed, ſhall be therein named, mentioned, or expreſſed to be pardoned,) Nor to enure to reſtore to any perſon or perſons, Bodies Politick or Corporate, other then then the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Lord Steward of his Majeſties Houſhold, and other the Proteſtants of <hi>IRELAND</hi>) and their Heirs, and ſuch other perſon and perſons as in, and by an Act intended hereafter to be Paſſed, ſhall be therein named, mentioned, or expreſſed in that behalf, any Eſtate, Liberties, Franchiſes, or Hereditaments in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſold, or diſpoſed of by both, or either Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any Convention aſſuming the Stile or Name of a Parliament, or any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deriving Authority from them, or any of them, or which was approved or confirmed by them, or any of them; Nor to the Mean Profits, Rents, or contingencies of advantage of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And it is further Provided and Enacted, That every perſon or perſons hereby pardoned, may plead the general iſſue, without ſpecial pleading of this pardon, and give this Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in evidence for his diſcharge, and that the ſame ſhall be thereupon allowed, and the advantage thereof had as fully to all intens and purpoſes, as if the ſame had been fully and well pleaded; And in ſuch manner as any Juſtice of the Peace, Conſtable, or other Officer, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned for matters acted by them as Officers, or in execution of their Offices, may have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the matter of their juſtification, upon the general Iſſue by them pleaded, by the Laws and Statutes of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:180550:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Provided alſo, That this Act nor any thing therein contained, ſhall Extend or be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted to extend to Pardon any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, for any Theft or Stealing of any goods, or other Felonies, ſince the fourth day of <hi>March</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thouſand ſix hundred fifty and nine, any thing in this Act contained to the contrary thereof in any wiſe Notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That neither this Act nor any thing therein contained, ſhall Extend to Acquit or Diſcharge any perſon or perſons, from making Reſtitution of all ſuch Rents, Sums of Money, Horſes, Cattle, or other Goods, which by a certain Act, or pretended Act lately made, Entituled, <hi>An Act for Repeal of two Acts for Sequeſtrations,</hi> Are required to be reſtored to thoſe from whom they were taken; Nor ſhall this preſent Act be conſtrued to Diſable, or Bar the Reſpective Owners, or Proprietors, of and from their Several and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Actions, or Suits at Law, or in Equitie, for, or by reaſon of the ſaid, or any other Rents, Moneys, Horſes, Cattle, or Goods, which ſince the Five and twentieth day of <hi>July,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty and nine, have been by any perſon or perſons wrongfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, or taken away, and for which the ſaid wrong doers are not in any wiſe Indempnified by the ſaid or any other Act of Repeal.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That no perſon or perſons who by virtue of any Order or Warrant mediately or immediately derived from His late Majeſtie, or His Majeſtie that now is, or by virtue of any Act, Ordinance or Order of any or both Houſes of Parliament, or any of the Authorities aforeſaid, or any Committee or Committees acting under them, or any of them, have Seized, Sequeſtred, Leavied, Advanced or paid to any Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Uſe, or into any Publick Treaſury within this Kingdom, any Goods, Chattels. Debts, Rents, Sum or Sums of Money belonging to any perſon or perſons whatſoever, ſhall hereafter be Sued, Moleſted or Drawn into Queſtion for the ſame, but that they and every of them ſhall be Diſcharged againſt all perſons for ſo much and no more of the ſaid Goods, Chartels, Debts, Rents, Sum or Sums of Money, as their ſeveral and reſpective Orders of Diſcharge or Acquittances extend unto.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That nothing herein contained ſhall extend to Diſcharge any perſon or perſons who have been by private Order or inſtructions imployed and intruſted, or have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken the imployment to Receive any Sum or Sums of Money for the Kings Majeſties Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice or Supply, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce the Year One thouſand ſix hundred forty and eight, from making their Accompts for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That this Act ſhall not extend to pardon or Diſcharge from Accompt to the Kings Majeſtie, any perſon or perſons for any Sum or Sums of Money received for that illegal Tax of Decimation, or upon the Accompt of any Militia ſettled or acted in ſince One thouſand ſix hundred forty and eight, and not Accompted for, or paid over, or Diſcharged to or by any that had Authority, or pretended Authority to Diſcharge the reſpective Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That if any perſon or perſons being His Majeſties Meſnial Servant or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, or having or pretending to have received particular Intructions or Directions from His Majeſtie, have during the time of ſuch his or their relation unto His Majeſtie, or whileſt he or they were acting, or pretending to act for His Majeſties Intereſt, in purſuance of the ſaid Inſtructions or Directions, Wilfully, Malitiouſly and Traiterouſly held Intelligence with any Forain Prince or Princes, State or States, or with any perſon or perſons uſurping Supreme Authoritie in this Kingdom, or other His Majeſties Dominions, or with their or either of their Miniſters or Agents, and without His Majeſties licence, and to the intent to betray His Majeſties Perſon or Counſels, or have received any Sum or Sums of Money, or Penſion for ſuch Treachery, That then ſuch perſon and perſons, as to the Offence in this Proviſo mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall be and is hereby Excepted out of this Act, any thing herein contained to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtanding; ſo as ſuch Perſon or Perſons be Outlawed, or otherwiſe legally Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of ſuch Offence or Offences within the ſpace of Two years from the Five and twentieth day of <hi>April,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty.</p>
            <p>Provided, That this Act of General Pardon, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the Pardoning or Diſcharging of any Debts or Sums of Money due to or for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize of any Goods or Merchandiſe, whereof any Entries have been made in the Cuſtom Houſe, which have grown due ſince the Twenty fifth day of <hi>March,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty and eight, or to the Pardoning or Diſcharging of any Debts or Sums of Money due to the Farmers, or pretended Farmers of Excize, ſince the Twenty fifth day of <hi>March,</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and ſix hundred fifty and ſeven.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That this Act, nor any thing therein contained, ſhall extend to Pardon, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge,
<pb facs="tcp:180550:7"/>or give any other Benefit whatſoever unto <hi>John Liſle, William Say,</hi> Sir <hi>Hardreſs Waller, Valentine Wauton, Thomas Harriſon, Edward Whalley, William Heveningham, Iſaac Penington, Henry Martin, John Barkstead, Gilbert Millington, Edmund Ludlow,</hi> Sir <hi>Michael Liveſey, Robert Titchborn, Owen Row, Robert Lilburn, Adrian Scroop, John Okey, John Hewſon, William Goff, Cornelius Holland, Thomas Challoner, John Carew, John Jones, Miles Corbet, Henry Smith, Gregory Clement, Thomas Wogan, Edmond Harvey, Thomas Scot, William Cawley, John Downs, Nicholas Love, Vincent Potter, Auguſtine Garland, John Dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, George Fleetwood, Simon Meyn, James Temple, Peter Temple, Daniel Blagrave, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Wait, John Cook, Andrew Broughton, Edward Dendy, William Hewlet, Hugh Peters, Francis Hacker, Daniel Axtel,</hi> nor any of them, nor to thoſe Two perſons, or either of them who being Diſguiſed by Frocks and Vizors did appear upon the Scaffold erected before <hi>Whitehall</hi> upon the Thirtieth of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred forty and eight: All which Perſons for their Execrable Treaſon, in Sentencing to death, or Signing the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Horrid Murther, or being inſtrumental in taking away the precious Liſe of Our late Soveraign Lord CHARLES the Firſt of Glorious Memory, are left to be proceeded againſt as Traitors to his late Majeny, according to the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> and are out of this preſent Act wholly Excepted and Foreprized.</p>
            <p>But in regard the ſaid <hi>Owen Row, Auguſtine Garland Edmond Harvey. Henry Smith, Henry Martin,</hi> Sir <hi>Hardreſs Waller, Robert Titchborn, George Fleetwood, Iames Temple, Thomas Wait, Simon Meyn, William Heveningham, Iſaac Penington, Peter Temple, Robert Lilburn, Gilbert Millington, Vincent Potter, Thomas Wogan,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Downs,</hi> have perſonally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared and rendred themſelves (according to the Proclamation bearing Date the Sixth day of <hi>Iune,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty, to Summon the Perſons therein named, who gave Judgment and Aſſiſted in the ſaid Horrid and Deteſtable Murther of our ſaid late So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, to appear and render themſelves) and do pretend thereby to ſome favor, upon ſome conceived doubtful Words in the ſaid Proclamation;</p>
            <p>Be it Enacted by this preſent Parliament, and the Authority of the ſame (upon the humble deſires of the Lords and Commons in Parliament Aſſembled) That if the ſaid <hi>Owen Row, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine Garland, Edmond Harvey, Henry Smith, Henry Martin,</hi> Sir <hi>Har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſs Waller, Robert Titchborn George Fleetwood, Iames Temple, Thomas Wait, Simon Meyn, Willtam H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningham, Iſaac Penington, Peter Temple, Robert Lilburn, Gilbert Millington, Vincent Poeter, Thomas W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gan</hi> and <hi>Iohn Downs,</hi> or any of them, ſhall be legally Attainted for the Horrid Treaſon and Murther aforeſaid; that then, nevertheleſs, the Execution of the ſaid Perſon and Perſons ſo Attainted ſhall be ſuſpended, until His Majeſty by the Adviſe and Aſſent of the Lords and Commons in Parliament, ſhall Order the Execution by Act of Parliament to be paſſed for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Except alſo out of this preſent Act <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Henry Ireton</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Iohn Bradſhaw</hi> deceaſed, and <hi>Thomas Pride</hi> deceaſed.</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this Act contained ſhall extend to Diſcharge the Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Goods. Chattels, Rights, Truſts, and other the Hereditaments late of the ſaid <hi>Oliver Cromwel, Henry Ireton, Iohn Bradſhaw</hi> and <hi>Thomas Pride;</hi> or of <hi>Iſaac Ewer</hi> deceaſed, Sir <hi>Iohn Danvers</hi> deceaſed, Sir <hi>Thomas Maleverer</hi> Baronet, deceaſed, <hi>William Purefoy</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Iohn Blakiſton</hi> deceaſed, Sir <hi>William Conſtable</hi> Baronet, deceaſed, <hi>Richard Dean</hi> decealed, <hi>Francis Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ya</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Peregrin Pelham</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Iohn Moor</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Iohn Aldred,</hi> alias <hi>Alured,</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Humphrey Edwards</hi> deceaſed, Sir <hi>Gregory Norton</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>et deceaſed, <hi>Iohn Venn</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Thomas Andrews</hi> Alderman, deceaſed, <hi>Anthony Stapely</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Thomas Horton</hi> deceaſed. <hi>Iohn Fry</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Thomas Hamond</hi> deceaſed, Sir <hi>Iohn Bourchler</hi> deceaſed, of and from ſuch Pains, Penalties and Forfeitures, as by one other Act of Parliament intended to be hereafter Paſſed for that purpoſe, ſhall be Expreſſed and Declared.</p>
            <p>And alſo Except out of this preſent Act, <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Mounſon, Iames Challoner,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Mildmay,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Harrington, Iohn Phelps,</hi> and <hi>Robert Wallop;</hi> All which perſons did Act and Sit in that Traiterous Aſlembly, which in the Month of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1648 acted and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt the Life of our late Soveraign, King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt of bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; and are therefore reſerved to ſuch Pains, Penalties and Forfeitures, not extending to Liſe as by another Act intended to be paſſed for that purpoſe ſhall be impoſed on them.</p>
            <p>And alſo Except Sir <hi>Arthur H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſilrigg,</hi> for and in reſpect onely of ſuch Pains, Penalties and Forfeitures, not extending to Life, as by one Act intended to be hereafter paſſed for that purpoſe ſhall be Inflicted and Impoſed.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That <hi>Iohn Hutchinſon</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> and <hi>Francis Laſſells,</hi> ſhall be and are hereby made for ever incapable to Execute any Place or Office of Truſt, Civil or Military, within
<pb facs="tcp:180550:7"/>this Kingdom; And that the ſaid <hi>Franeis Laſſells</hi> ſhall pay unto our Soveraign Lord the King. One <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> years value of his Eſtate, Any thing herein before contained to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not extend to the Pardoning, or to give any other benefit whatſoever unto Sir <hi>Henry Vane, Iohn Lambert,</hi> or either of them, but that they and either of them, are and ſhall be out of this preſent Act wholly, Excepted and Foreprized.</p>
            <p>Provided that if <hi>William Lenthall, VVilliam Burton, Oliver St. Iohn, Iohn Ireton</hi> Alderman, Col <hi>VVilliam Sydenham,</hi> Col. <hi>Iohn Deſborow, Iohn Blackwel</hi> of <hi>Moreclack, Chriſtopher Pack</hi> Alderman, <hi>Richard Keeble, Charles Fleetwood, Iohn Pyne, Richard Dean,</hi> Maj. <hi>Richard Creed, Philip Nye</hi> Clerk, <hi>Iohn Goodwyn</hi> Clerk, Sir <hi>Gilbert Pickering,</hi> Colonel <hi>Thomas Liſter,</hi> and Col. <hi>Ralph Cobbet,</hi> ſhall after the Firſt day of <hi>September</hi> 1660 accept, or exercize any Office Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, Civil or Military, or any other Publique Employment within this Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Dominion of <hi>VVales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed</hi> that then ſuch Perſon or Perſons as do to accept or execute as aforeſaid, ſhall to all intents and purpoſes in Law ſtand as if he or they had been totally excepted by name in this Act.</p>
            <p>Provided likewiſe, That all thoſe who ſince the Fifth of <hi>December,</hi> One thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred forty eight, did give Sentence of Death upon any Perſon or Perſons, in any of the late Illegal and Tyrannical High Courts of Juſtice in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>VVales,</hi> or ſigned the Warrant for Execution of any Perſon there condemned (except Colonel <hi>Richard Iugoldſby,</hi> and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Matthew Thomlinſon</hi>) ſhall be and are hereby made incapable of bearing any Office. Eccleſiaſtical, Civil or Military within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or Dominion of <hi>VVales,</hi> or of ſerving as a Member in any Parliament after the Firſt day of <hi>September,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo and it is Enacted, That all and every the Perſons appointed Truſtees in a late pretended Act or Ordinance made in the year of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred forty nine, for and concerning Tithes appropriate, Oblations, Obventions, Penſions, Portions of Tithes appropriate, Offerings, Fee-farm Rents, iſſuing out of the Tithes therein mentioned, Firſt-fruits and other things, and Enacted or mentioned to be Enacted to be veſted, ſettled, adjudged, or deemed to be in the actual Seiſin or poſſeſſion of ſuch Perſon and Perſons in the ſaid pretended Act or Ordinance mentioned, and their Heirs, ſhall account for and be reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for all Rents and Profits of the Premiſes which came to their hands, and have not been by the ſaid Truſtees or their Order disburſed, diſpoſed or imployed, for the maintenance of Miniſters or other uſes, according to the ſaid pretended Act or Ordinance, or ſome other Act. Order or Ordinance made in the years of our Lord, 1650, 1654, and 1656. by any Aſſemlby called or reputed a Parliament, or aſſuming the power of Parliament, according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of ſuch Act, Acts, or Ordinances, and the Agents and Receivers under the Order of the ſaid Truſtees, and the Occupiers and Tenants of the Premiſſes, who have taken the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes or profits thereof into their hands, without agreement to pay Rent therefore, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> made no account or ſatisfaction to the Truſtees aforeſaid, or to ſome other by their Order; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo the Perſons who have held the ſame, or taken the profits thereof under any agreement to pay Rent or Money for the ſame, and have not paid the ſame, ſhall reſpectively account, pay and make ſatisfaction for ſo much of the Premiſſes, and profits of the premiſſes as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied or unaccounted for as aforeſaid, and pay ſuch Arrearages of Rents or Money, as by ſuch Agreement remaineth unpaid by them: all which payments and accounts ſhall be made to ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and in ſuch maner as in Parliament ſhall be directed. Nevertheleſs it is not hereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, That any Miniſter, Schoolmaſter, or other Perſon for whoſe benefit or maintenance the ſaid pretended Acts or Ordinances were made, ſhall be accountable or lyable to make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for any Profits, Rents, or ſums of Money paid to, or taken by them reſpectively, by virtue or colour of any Order or Appointment of the ſaid Truſtees, or any of them, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That this Act do not extend to Pardon any Bond taken in his late Majeſties Name, before the Month of <hi>May</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred forty two, for ſecuring the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per debt of any Servant or Receiver of the Revenue of His ſaid late Majeſtie, that hath not been paid to or by Order of ſome lawfull or pretended Authority; And whereas by an Order of the ſix and twentieth day of <hi>May</hi> in the year One thouſand ſix hundred forty one, the then Houſe of Commons in Parliament did accept the ſum of One hundred and fifty thou and pounds, as a Compoſition from the Farmers of ſeveral Cuſtoms, Voted to be Illegally taken, and ſome of the ſaid Farmers did procure and pay the ſaid whole ſum of One hundred and fifty thouſand pounds at the deſire of the ſaid Houſe of Commons, and upon their Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:180550:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180550:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180550:9"/>that ſuch of the ſaid Farmers as did not pay their proportions, ſhould not be Pardoned but proceeded againſt, and out of their Fines Satisfaction ſhould be made to thoſe who had paid the aid One hundred and fifty thouſand pounds, and in purſuance thereof did on the Firſt of <hi>June</hi> then next following, Reſolve, That the Eſtates of ſuch Perſons living or dead, as have by colour of any Patent received moneys from the Subject under pretence of ſuch Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns or have been under-ſharers with the Patentees, ought to be made liable to Reſtitution; It is therefore Provided, That this Act ſhall not extend nor be conſtrued to extend to Pardon or Indem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nifie any Perſon or Perſons, their Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators or Aſſigns, who have not paid their proportions of the ſaid One hundred and fifty thouſand pounds, or ought to have been contributary thereunto, from or againſt Miſdemeanors or Offences re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the ſaid Cuſtoms, or from payment of their Proportions: But that the Eſtates of the dead, aſwell as of the living, of ſuch who ought to have been Contributary, in whoſe poſſeſſion ſoever (Purchaſers <hi>Bona fide,</hi> and upon valuable conſiderations onely excepted) ſhall continue, and be charged and chargeable with the payment of their Proportions to all intent and purpoſes as if this Act had not been made, any thing herein contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not extend or be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued to Pardon or Diſcharge any Sum or Sums of Money due and in Arrear for Exciſe of Beer, Ale, or other Native or Inland Commodity, ſince the Twenty fourth day of <hi>Iune,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty and nine</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That nothing in this Act contained ſhall extend to the Pardoning or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of any Sum or Sums of money, due from any Officers or Souldiers to any of the Subjects of this Kingdom for Free quarter, ſince the Second day of <hi>Iuly</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty and nine, or to Diſcharge any moneys borrowed by any Officers for preventing of Free quarter.</p>
            <p>Provided always and be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That no Conveyance, Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Grant, Bargain, Sale, Charge, Leaſe, Aſſignment of Leaſe, Grants, and Surrenders by Copy of Court-Roll, Eſtate, Intereſt, Truſt, or Limitation of any uſe or uſes, of any Mannors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, not being the Lands, nor Hered taments of the late King. Queen, Prince, or of any Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Deans or Chapters, nor being Lands, or Hereditaments, Sold or given or appointed to be Sold or given for the Delinquencie, or pretended Delinquency of any perſon or perſons whatſoever, by virtue or pretext of any Act, Order or Ordinance, or reputed Act, Order or Ordinance, ſince the Firſt day of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1641, nor any Statute, Judgment, or Recognizance had made, acknowledged or ſuffered, to any perſon or perſons, Bodies politick or Corporate, before the Nine and twentieth day of <hi>September,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty and nine, by any of the perſons before in this Act by name excepted, or their Heirs, or by any other perſon or perſons claiming by, from, or under them, or any of them, other than the Wife or Wives, Childe, Children, Heir and Heirs of ſuch perſon and perſons or any of them, for money <hi>Bona fide</hi> to them or any of them paid or lent; nor any Conveyance, Aſſurance, Grant, or Eſtate made before the Five and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>April,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty, by any perſon or perſons to any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perſon or perſons excepted by name as aforeſaid, in Truſt and for the Benefit of any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, Bodies politick or Corporate not excepted by name as aforeſaid, ſhall be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached, Defeated, made void, or fruſtrated hereby, or by the attainder or conviction of any ſuch excepted perſon or perſons, but that the ſame ſhall be held and enjoyed by the Purchaſers Grantees, Leſlees, Aſſignees, <hi>Ceſtuy que uſe, Ceſtuy que truſt,</hi> and every of them, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Executors, Adminiſtrators, and Aſſigns reſpectively, as if this Act had not been made, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> if the ſaid perſon or perſons had not been excepted, attainted, or Convicted, any Law, Stature, Uſage, or Cuſtom to the contrary thereof in any w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That this Act, nor any thing therein contained ſhall not extend to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnifie any perſon or perſons whatſoever, who have entered into any Meſſuages, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments called Fabrick Lands, or poſſeſt themſelves of any Rent or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues given for the repair of any Cathedral or other Church, or who have Sacrilegiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched themſelves by converting the Plate, or Utenſils and Materials of or belonging to ſuch Churches to their own private uſe and advantage, for or in reſpect of the ſaid Crimes onely.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
